Freeman: 我们的存在是有意为之的吗？
Freeman: Were we put here on
purpose by someone or something?
还是一些随机事件创造了
Or did some random event create
我们今日看到的复杂生命？
all of the incredible complexity
we see today?
[嘶嘶声]
[ Hisses ]
Freeman: 科学家一直在努力理解
Freeman: Scientists
have been trying to understand
生命的起源...
how life was created...
[相机快门声]
[ Camera shutter clicks ]
但我们的理解仍有许多空白。
But there are still gaps
in our understanding.
我们是更高级力量的作品，
Could our existence
be the work of a higher power
还是自然法则造就的？
or was it the laws of nature?
[雷声轰鸣]
[ Thunder cracks ]
神创造了进化吗？
Did God create evolution?
空间，时间，生命本身，
Space, time, life itself.
宇宙的奥秘尽在穿越虫洞。
The secrets of the cosmos
lie through the wormhole.
Captions by vitac...
www.Vitac.Com.
Translated by Allegro1756
Captions paid for by Discovery Communications.
Sync & Corrected by Iscol.
科学家估计
Scientists estimate
地球上大约生活过数十亿个物种，
that billions of species
have lived on earth
从最小的微生物，到50吨重的恐龙。
from the tiniest microbes
to a 50-ton dinosaur.
圣经说上帝在六天内做出了它们，
The Bible says God made them all
in six days.
但还有另一个理论...
But there's another theory...
生命在大约四十亿年前自发产生，
life created itself
about four billion years ago,
而已知地球上繁多的物种
and the myriad species
earth has known
全部是由进化产生的。
have all been the product
of evolution.
神学和科学
Theology and the science
都希望能够找到它们的共同之处。
struggle to find a common ground.
当查尔斯・达尔文提出进化论时
Did Charles Darwin get it right
算是正确解释了生命起源吗？
when he proposed that evolution
created all life?
还是生命是由上帝赋予的？
Was it the guiding hand
of some supreme being?
亦或二者都是可能的？
Or could it have been both?
我以前经常在家附近的
I used to find caterpillars
树丛中寻找毛虫...
in the bushes near my house
growing up...
又肥又粗短的虫子。
fat, stubby worms.
不久之后，它们就会把自己包在茧中。
Before long, each one hid away
inside a silky cocoon.
我对这小小的虫茧中正发生着的很好奇，
I wondered what was going on
inside that tiny shelter.
如此丑陋的毛虫是如何
How did something so ugly
变成美丽的蝴蝶的？
transform into a beautiful butterfly?
Michael Behe是宾夕法尼亚州理海大学的
Michael Behe is a biochemist
from lehigh university
生物化学家。
in Pennsylvania.
他是“智慧设计论”的支持者...
He's an advocate for an idea
called intelligent design...
这种理论是指有什么人或什么东西
that someone or something
在地球上埋下生命的种子，
planted the seeds of life
on earth
然后指导其进化。
and has had a guiding hand
in its evolution ever since.
Behe: 智慧设计论表明随机进程
Behe: Intelligent design argues
that random processes
是不能产生今日所见到的生命的，
can't produce
what we see in life today,
但它并不与古代生命
but it has no quarrel
with the idea of descent
发展到现代生命的观点相矛盾。
from ancient organisms
to modern organisms.
Freeman: Michael与达尔文进化论的矛盾在于
Freeman: Michael's problem
with Darwin's theory
达尔文坚持随机突变造就了进化。
is that Darwin insists evolution
stems from random mutations.
但当他观察大自然时，
When he looks around in nature,
Michael发现很多东西看起来
he sees plenty of things
that look like
像是随机放在一起的，
they were
randomly thrown together,
像这些木头碎片。
like the debris in these woods.
最近这里发生了一场风暴，
We had a storm
pass through here recently.
没人会认为这种场面
Nobody would think
that any of this
是有人故意摆放成这样的。
was particularly arranged
on purpose.
你也能看到这是一团乱麻。
You know, it's just a jumble.
这有根树枝，
Here's a stick here.
那里也有个树枝，还有块石头。
There's a stick there,
a stone there.
Freeman: 但Michael认为自然界中有些东西
Freeman: But Michael believes
other things in nature
是不可能随机出现的，
could not have arranged
themselves randomly.
它们像是经过刻意设计的。
They appear to be
the work of a designer.
就像这些树枝不可能随机排列成
Just as these sticks didn't
randomly arrange themselves
“Life(生命)”这个单词，Michael不认为
into the word "Life, "
Michael doesn't believe
生命也不会随机出现。
biological life
came together randomly, either.
Behe: 我是一名生物化学家，所以我看到了自然界中
Behe: I'm a biochemist,
and so I see evidence in nature
大多数人不会考虑的证据，
and places where most people
don't think about,
因为它就在细胞中。
but it's in the cell.
细胞是一个奇妙的纳米尺度的工厂，
The cell is
a fantastic nano-scale factory
其中有机器...由分子组成的机器。
with machinery... literally
machines made out of molecules.
Freeman: Michael研究了细菌的结构。
Freeman: Michael studies
the structure of bacteria.
一些细菌具有叫做鞭毛的尾，
Some bacteria have tails
called flagella
这样它就可以游动。
that allow them to swim.
Behe: 这非常类似于舷外发动机，
Behe: It is quite literally
an outboard motor
细菌靠它就可以游动，
that bacteria use to swim,
就像我们每天看到的舷外发动机，
and just like an outboard motor
in our everyday life,
鞭毛具有夹子可以固定到细菌的细胞膜上，
it's got clamps to hold it
on to the bacterial membrane,
还有螺旋桨叶可以旋转。
it's got a propeller
that spins 'round and around.
如果你把其中的一部分或几部分拿走，
Turns out if you remove
one of more of these pieces,
鞭毛就无法工作了。
the flagellum
doesn't work at all.
Freeman: 细菌尾巴的复杂结构
Freeman: The complicated
structure of bacterial tails
使Michael发展出了他称之为
“不可简约的复杂性”的理论。
led Michael to develop a theory
he calls irreducible complexity.
这个理论认为生命系统需要其所有的部分
It claims that living systems
need all of their parts
才能工作，
in order to work.
它们不可能某一部分单独进化。
They can't evolve
piece by piece.
而达尔文的进化论则要求这种部件的渐进进化，
So, Darwin's theory
requires this gradualism,
这种模式中生物的特征是随时间缓慢演化的。
wherein some feature of biology
is built up slowly over time.
但在不可简约的复杂性系统中...
But with
an irreducibly complex system...
一个系统拥有数个组成部件...
that means a system that has
a number of components...
你不能随时间逐渐构建出系统来让其工作。
you can't build it up gradually
over time and have it work.
Freeman: 如果细菌的鞭毛只丢失了一个组件，
Freeman: If the tail of the bacterium
was missing just one part,
那么整个鞭毛都无法工作。
the whole thing
wouldn't function.
Michael不认为
Michael doesn't think
有机体可以单纯的通过进化
organisms could have made
such leaps of complexity
来完成这种向复杂性的剧变。
through evolution alone.
他认为生命接受了造物主的帮助。
He thinks they must have had
help from a creator.
我是一名基督教徒，
I'm a Christian,
我当然认为神创造了宇宙，
and so I certainly think
God created the universe,
但我认为智慧设计论
but the nice thing
about intelligent design
可以让你意识到有些东西是被设计好的
is that you can realize
something was designed
而你不需要知道设计者是谁,
without knowing
who the designer was.
但你可以对他设计的东西充满信心。
But you can be confident
of the design.
Freeman: 细菌尾巴的复杂设计
Freeman: The complex design
of bacteria tails
还不是最神秘的生物学空白。
isn't the most mysterious leap
in biology.
还有更为复杂的结构，
There are
even more complex structures
更难以解释，
that are harder to explain,
比如脊椎动物的椎骨棘突。
like the bony spines
of vertebrates.
脊椎动物最早的祖先
Our earliest
vertebrate ancestors
有着叫做“脊索”的原始脊柱....
had backbones call notochords...
但却不是骨头，而是由胶原构成的柔韧的棒状物。
boneless, flexible rods made of collagen.
脊索至今仍存在于一些大型的淡水鱼类中。
Some big, freshwater fish that
are alive today still have them.
像我们这样的物种，在背部进化出了骨骼...
Other species, like us, have
evolved bones in the back...
形成了脊柱。
vertebral columns.
但条状脊索是如何
But how did long strips
of collagen make the leap
成为脊柱的呢？
and become bony spines?
瓦萨学院的生物机器人学家John Long
Bioroboticist John long
at vassar college
正在寻找这些消失的联系。
is searching
for these missing links.
我们感兴趣的问题之一
One of the great questions
we're interested in
就是我们所属的称为脊椎动物的群体
is how did this group of animals
that we belong to
是如何先进化的？
called vertebrates
first evolve?
这都是五亿年前的事情了，
Now, this happened
500 million years ago,
我们没有时间机器来回到过去
so we don't have a time machine
we can jump in, unfortunately,
看都发生了什么。
and go back
and see what happened.
Freeman: John认为第一个脊柱
Freeman: John suspects the first
versions of the vertebral column
是我们DNA中出现的小错误，
were small mistakes in our DNA
使得骨沉积在脊索上。
that created little
bony deposits on the notochord.
这些错误保留了下来，
They stuck around
because they ended up
因为它们使动物变得更快更强，寻找食物更容易。
making animals faster, stronger,
and better at finding food.
但古代鱼类化石表明
But fossils of ancient fish
这种进化是一步就完成的，
don't tell this
evolutionary story step by step.
化石记录中存在许多巨大的历史缺口。
There are huge gaps
in the historical record.
John于是决定填补上这些缺口，
So John has decided
to try and fill in these gaps
通过将已灭绝的生物复活...
by bringing extinct creatures
back to life...
比如这些机器人。
As robots.
欢迎来到Abyss(深渊)。
Welcome to the abyss.
我们在这个水池中创造了一个人造世界，
We create an artificial world
here in this tank
我们可以通过游动的仿生机器人重塑
for our swimming biorobots
where we reanimate evolution
五亿年前的进化过程。
that happened
500 million years ago.
Freeman: John称它们叫做Evolvobots(进化机器人)，
Freeman: John's robots
are called evolvobots.
它们正准备开始生命这场游戏。
They are about to play
the game of life.
Long: 这是一根仿生脊柱
Long: This is
a biomimetic vertebral column
由胶原制成，
that's specially designed
out of collagen,
我们可以改变脊椎的个数，
and we can vary
the number of vertebrae,
这也是我们能够使其进化的特征。
and this is the feature
that we're allowing to evolve.
Freeman: John赋予其的脊索，
Freeman: John has given them notochords
由不同数目的脊椎组成，
that can each be segmented with
different numbers of vertebrae,
从0到5，到10或是15。
from 0 to 5 to 10 to 15.
在他创造的世界中，光意味着生命和食物，
He has created a world in which
light means life or food.
进化机器人的任务就是找到它们的食物。
The evolvobots' task
is to find their next dinner.
Long: 我们从0开始，到5、10和15根脊椎，
Long: So, we go
from 0 to 5 to 10 to 15,
我们希望得到的结果是
and what we're expecting
to have happen, right,
拥有脊椎数最多的机器人
is that the robots
with the most vertebrae,
就像这个，
over here,
比脊椎最少的机器人可以获得更多的食物。
will out-compete the robots
with the fewest vertebrae.
那么结果应该是金牌获得者、
So, this should be
gold-medal winner,
银牌获得者、铜牌获得者
silver-medal winner,
bronze-medal winner,
以及感谢参与。
and thank you for trying.
现在落后的像是0个脊椎的机器人。
Now, dragging way behind now,
looks like zero vertebrae.
Freeman: 有着分段脊柱的进化机器人
Freeman: The evolvobots
with segmented backbones
比没有分段的表现更为出色。
are performing better
than the one without.
Long: 分10段的现在位于首位，
Long: Look at number 10...
way out in front now.
接着是分5段的，
And then we have number 5,
分15段的在边上，不过慢一些。
and 15 over on the side there
is getting there, but slowly.
Freeman: 让John惊讶的是，
Freeman: To John's surprise,
有着10根脊椎骨的机器人打败了有着15根的。
the evolvobot with 10 bones won,
beating the one with 15.
Long: 那么我们能得到什么样的结论呢？
Long: So, what do we have emerging here?
似乎中等脊椎数量的
It looks like
intermediate number of vertebrae
更擅长寻找食物。
is doing a better job
at getting food.
所以脊椎数目并不是关键，
So it's not just having
a bunch of vertebrae,
关键在于其数目是否合适。
it's having the right number.
Freeman: John认为这表明了
Freeman: John believes this shows
进化并不是一个设计好的过程。
that evolution
is not a designed process.
大自然可以已经随机试过了不同种类的脊柱，
Nature may have randomly tried
different kinds of backbones,
只是最合适的存活了下来。
and the best ones survived.
我们发现如果存在一种增强觅食及
We find that when there's
selection pressure
逃跑能力的选择压力，
for enhanced feeding
and fleeing,
就足够能驱动脊柱的进化。
this is sufficient to drive
the evolution of vertebrae.
Freeman: 通过他的研究，
Freeman: Using his research,
John可以追踪脊柱的发展进程，
John can trace
the path of backbone evolution
直到我们现在的脊柱。
all the way up to us.
Long: 作为人类，一直困扰我们的想法是
Long: So, as humans,
we get bothered by the idea
我们进化出
that we could have evolved,
如此发达头脑的荣耀，
in all our wonderful,
brain-heavy glory,
只是一些随机过程，
by random processes,
而让我们苦苦思索的
but one of the hard things
成为人类的难事之一
to wrap your head around
as a human being
就是进化并不是经过设计的，
is that evolution works
not by design
而是无人控制的自发行为。
but by hands-off
emergent principles.
Freeman: John的进化机器人向我们展示了
Freeman: John's evolvobots
give us a window
原始生物是如何进化成为
into how primitive organisms
can evolve
复杂的人类的。
into upright,
complex human beings.
但地球是否拥有足够的时间
But has there been enough time
in the history of earth
来进行缓慢而又不稳定的进化呢？
for this slow and unsteady
process of evolution to happen?
一位麻省理工的复杂性理论学家
正在通过计算来找出答案。
An M.I.T. Complexity theorist
is doing the math to find out.
达尔文的进化论主要基于
Darwin's theory of evolution
物种通过遗传物质的错误及改变
hinges on the idea
that species gradually evolve
来实现逐渐的进化的。
through a process
of genetic trial and error.
在地球生命产生的40亿年中，
In the four-billion-year history
of life on earth,
进化学家认为
evolutionists argue,
我们都是从第一个单细胞生命进化来的。
the first single-celled
organisms evolved to become me.
相信智慧设计论的人认为
Those who believe
in intelligent design
遗传物质的错误及改变
argue that trial and error
在这四十亿年中无法创造出
could never create
something so complex
如此复杂的生命。
in that amount of time.
进化论也需要计算吗？
Does the theory of evolution
add up?
这是个只有数学家能回答的问题。
That's a question
only a mathematician can answer.
当麻省理工的Scott Aaronson教授长大的时候，
When M.I.T. Professor
Scott Aaronson was growing up,
他有一个很大的梦想。
he had big dreams.
我小时候
When I was a kid,
一生的梦想是创造自己的电子游戏。
my dream in life was to create
my own video games.
电子游戏让我感到惊讶，
You know,
video games just amazed me.
它就像是整个世界的微缩版，
They were like these entire
worlds in miniature,
然而又不同于真实世界，
and yet, you know,
unlike with the real world,
一定有谁很清楚这些
模拟的世界是如何运作的，对吧？
someone must understand
exactly how they work, right?
因为有人制作了它们。
Because someone made them.
Freeman: Scott经常想象游戏中的人物
Freeman: Scott used to imagine that
the characters in his video games
就像是机器一样在工厂中生产出来，
were built in a factory
like machines.
最后他发现
But he eventually figured out
它们实际上是通过数学建立的。
they were actually built
from math.
Aaronson: 你可以说“这是游戏，
Aaronson: You could say,
"Here is the game,
然后这是游戏的代码。”
and then here's the code
of the game."
而这些代码
and the code, you know,
并不是对游戏的某种描述，
is not just some description
of the game.
它的确是 游戏，对吧？
It is the game, right?
你改变代码，
You change the code,
你就可以看到游戏也发生了变化，
and then you can watch the game
do something different,
这就很像数学问题。
which is
really just a math problem.
这对于我就像是一种启示，
And, you know, for me,
I think that was a revelation
好像是刚得知婴儿从哪里来一样。
comparable to learning
where babies come from.
Freeman: 这种领悟激发了Scott
Freeman: This realization
inspired Scott
深入探究于数学理论
to look
for deep mathematical theories
来解决许多最大的科学谜团，
to solve the biggest mysteries
in science,
比如生物如何进化出现在的复杂性。
like how organisms evolved
into complex beings.
智慧设计论的信仰者认为
Believers in intelligent design
like to say
像自然选择这种随机进程
that for some random process
like natural selection
产生眼或鸟类的翅或人脑
to produce the eye or the wing
of a bird or the human brain
都是不可能的，
is about as improbable
就像是龙卷风扫过废物堆积场
as a toRNAdo passing
through a junkyard
是不可能自发组装成可使用的建筑的。
and somehow assembling
a usable building.
这就是我工作的地方，
This is where I work.
这里是麻省理工的史塔特中心(Stata center)，
It's called
the M.I.T. Stata center,
它看起来确实像是
and it does kind of look like
龙卷风经过之后。
a toRNAdo passed
through the place.
无论这栋建筑看起来如何，
This building,
despite how it may look,
都不是被自然进程设计的，
was not designed
by natural processes.
而是由建筑师Frank Gehry设计的，
It was designed
by the architect Frank Gehry,
但在数学和计算机科学中，
but in math
and computer science,
我们知道产生有趣的结构
we know that producing
interesting structure
并不一定需要设计者。
doesn't always require
a designer.
Freeman: 神创论者通常认为
Freeman: Creationists often argue
进化是随机的，穷尽于搜索
that evolution is a random,
exhaustive search
所有可能的生物学组合。
through all possible
biological combinations.
[呼哧]
[ Wheezes ]
这是一项不可能的任务，
An impossible task
无法在仅仅的四十亿年中
that could never have gotten
as far as it has
就达到像现在这样完美的地步。
in only four billion years.
[呼噜声]
[ Oinks ]
Scott认为像人脑这样的复杂组织
Scott believes complex traits
like the human brain
或细菌鞭毛
or a bacterium's tail
是能够在这个时间中进化出来的，
can evolve
in a reasonable amount of time
因为进化不是一个完全盲目的过程。
because evolution is not
a completely blind process.
实际上进化有一些巧妙的捷径。
In fact, evolution
has some clever shortcuts.
想象这块象棋棋盘是空白的，
Imagine this chessboard is blank
Scott的目标就是恰当为其上色
and Scott's goal
is to properly color it
使得相邻两块的
so that
no two neighboring squares
颜色不同。
are colored the same.
那么你会怎么做呢？
So, how could you do it?
我们可以想到
Well, there are
three different approaches
三种不同的方法。
that may spring to mind.
那就来让我的替身--超级Scott来试试吧。
Let's see my avatar,
super Scott, here, try to do it.
如果超级Scott拥有
If super Scott had
the magical powers
智慧设计者的魔力，
of an intelligent designer,
我假设，他就能
he could, I suppose,
在脑海中想到所有上色的可能，
just see in his mind's eye
all of the possible colorings
然后直接应用能够成立的上色方式。
and just instantly pick out
the one that worked.
Freeman: 对于智慧设计者超级Scott来说，
Freeman: If it takes just one step
一步为一个方格上色，
for the intelligent designer
super Scott to fill each square,
只需要花去他64步。
it would only take him 64 steps.
你只需几分钟就能创造人类，
You could create humans
in a matter of minutes
如果你有这种神一样的能力。
if you had this kind
of God-like vision.
Aaronson: 我们还能怎么做呢？
Aaronson: What else could we do?
一种暴力的方式...只是尝试所有上色的可能，
A brute-force approach... just
trying every possible coloring,
把所有可能的上色安排
every possible assignment
of colors,
适用到64个方格中，
to all 64 of the squares.
就需要2的64次方步
Well, there are
2 to the 64th power
来为棋盘的所有格子上色。
ways of coloring all the squares
of a chessboard.
大约是1.8的19次方步。
That's about 18 quintillion.
很明显他需要在这里耽误好大一会儿。
He's obviously gonna be at this
for quite a while.
Freeman: 在这种纯粹随机的任务中，
Freeman: On this purely random mission,
即使超级Scott只有一块不正确，
even if super Scott gets
all but one square correct,
他就需要全部重新开始。
he has to start over again.
如果生命照此进化，
Is organisms evolved like this,
从单细胞细菌进化到
it would take millions of times
longer
今日的智慧生命，
than the age of the universe
所花费的时间
for a single-celled bacterium
to evolve
是宇宙年龄的数百万倍。
into the intelligent life
we see today.
而进化是以不同的方式进行的。
But evolution works differently.
它会进行随机猜测，
It makes random guesses,
无论是否错误
but doesn't go
back to square one
都不会回到之前的方格中。
whenever it makes a mistake.
Aaronson: 超级Scott在完全随机的棋盘上开始上色，
Aaronson: Here, super Scott starts
out with a complete random coloring.
他会去寻找相同颜色的
He can just look
for any two squares
两个方格，随机挑选一个，
that are colored the same,
pick two of those at random,
并随机改变其颜色。
and then randomly change
the color of one of them.
Freeman: 在这种进化方式中，
Freeman: In this evolutionary approach,
超级Scott可以持续纠正棋盘颜色
super Scott can make corrections
along the way
而无需每次从头开始。
without having to start over
every time.
Aaronson: 你就会怀疑这样又会花多长时间呢？
Aaronson: But you might wonder
how long will this take?
结果当然是比
Well, it turns out
it will take longer
智慧设计者久，这是肯定的，
than the intelligent designer,
that's for sure.
另一方面，
On the other hand,
又远非暴力方式那么慢。
not nearly as long
as the brute-force approach.
为一个8乘8的棋盘上色，
With an eight by eight
chessboard,
随机突变的方式会花5000步。
this random-mutation approach
will take about 5,000 steps.
Freeman: 5000步多于64步，
Freeman: 5,000 steps is more than 64,
但比起1.8的19次方步少很多了。
but it's not anywhere near
18 quintillion.
这些关于进化的数学计算表明
These emerging mathematics
of evolution
复杂的结构可以惊人的速度产生。
show that complex patterns
can arise surprisingly quickly.
我们发现非刻意的进化过程
We've seen that
a mindless evolutionary process
的确能够解决进化问题，
really can solve the problem,
能够在有限的时间内进化出现有的复杂性。
and it can solve it without
an inordinate amount of time.
Freeman: Scott并未声称他证明了进化是如何进行的，
Freeman: Scott doesn't claim
he's proven evolution happened,
这只解决了地球时间表的问题。
only that it is possible
within earth's timeframe.
Aaronson: 对于我来说，科学态度
Aaronson: For me, the scientific attitude
并不在于世界上没有谜题，
is not that there are
no mysteries in the world.
而在于你不会困在谜题之中。
It's that you don't wallow
in mystery.
只有你持续寻找对问题的解释，
It's that you constantly look
for explanations of things,
如果你发现了对谜题的较好解释，
and, you know, if you find a
good explanation for something,
你就继续下去，
you go with it, you know,
至少到更好的解释出现的时候。
at least until a better
explanation comes along.
Freeman: 但在生命的公式中还有一个
Freeman: But there is
still one unknown variable
未知的变量。
in the equation of life.
亚利桑那州的一位化学家正在回溯时间
One chemist in Arizona
is rolling back the clock
寻找哪里产生了最原始的生命。
to figure out where the first
spark of life came from.
这颗星球上所有的生命都有一个共同点...
All living things on this planet
have one thing in common...
无论是植物、细菌，还是人类，
from plants to bacteria
to people,
所有的生命形式都使用了同样的
由DNA构成的遗传物质，
every life form uses the same
genetic material built from DNA
或与其相关的化学分子，RNA。
or its close chemical relative, RNA.
这对于认为所有的生命都起源于
This makes perfect sense
to evolutionists
一个共同的祖先的进化学家非常有意义，
who believe all life evolved
from a common ancestor,
但还有个意义更为深远的问题仍待解答，
but there is a more profound
question still to be answered.
如果DNA是生命的基础，那什么或谁造就了DNA？
If DNA is the spark of life,
what or who created DNA?
John Chaput是亚利桑那州立大学的一名化学家，
John Chaput, a chemist
at Arizona state university,
研究DNA的根源...
它到底从何而来
studies the roots of DNA...
where it came from
又如何持续存在这么久
and how it has survived
long enough
来产生复杂生命。
to produce complex life.
对于所有细胞，生存就需要DNA，
For all cells to survive,
they require DNA,
因为DNA含有遗传信息
which is the genetic information
或者说是生命的蓝图。
or the blueprint
for that organism.
细胞想要生存，就需要生长分裂，
And for cells to live,
they have to grow and divide,
在这个过程中，
and during that process,
DNA就需要经过复制
that DNA has to be copied
identically
确保遗传信息能够
so that you maintain
that genetic information
从一个细胞到下一个。
from one cell to the next.
Freeman: John正在扮演DNA聚合酶(复制DNA的酶)的角色。
Freeman: John is playing the role
of an enzyme called DNA polymerase.
他的工作就是将遗传编码
从一条DNA链上进行复制。
His job is to copy the code
of one DNA strand onto another.
Chaput: “A”与“T”互补，
Chaput: "A" Always
base pairs with "T, "
“C”与“G”互补。
and "C" Always base pairs
with "G."
Freeman: 但DNA无法自我复制，
Freeman: But DNA can't replicate
all by itself.
它需要“聚合酶”John来进行复制。
It require John, the polymerase,
to do the copying.
但在生命起初时是没有John的。
But at the first spark of life,
there was no John.
这对于进化论是个大问题。
It's a big problem
for the theory of evolution.
DNA应该不是
DNA could not have been
所有生命的分子基础，
the first molecular basis
for all of life
因为它不能自我复制。
because it can't copy itself.
如果不是DNA，那什么才是原始生命的基础呢？
If not DNA, what was
the first spark of life?
DNA很有可能是进化的产物，
It's quite possible that DNA
may be the product of evolution
生命历史中在DNA之前
and that other genetic materials
preceded it
还有其他遗传物质。
in the history of life.
Freeman: DNA是双螺旋结构，就像这根绳子。
Freeman: DNA has a double-helix
structure, like this rope.
在DNA之前的遗传物质
The genetic material
that came before it
应该能够结合到其复杂的结构上
would have to have been able
to bind with its complex shape
才能传递遗传信息。
in order to pass on
genetic information.
RNA是一个候选人，
One candidate is RNA,
RNA是我们现代细胞中存在的简化版DNA。
a simpler form of DNA that
is found in our cells today.
但如果我们观察RNA，就发现RNA同样很复杂，
But yet, if we look at RNA,
RNA is still very complicated,
在它之前可能还有
and it may have been preceded
更为简单的遗传物质。
by an even simpler
genetic material.
Freeman: RNA作为起初的遗传物质还太复杂，
Freeman: RNA is too complicated to
be the very first genetic material,
因为它的组分之一是称作核糖的复杂糖类。
because it's made of
a complex sugar called ribose.
想象下你是35亿年前的科学家，
Imagine you were a scientist
3.5 billion years ago
等着第一个生命的诞生。
waiting for the first spark of life.
为了形成RNA，五碳糖(核糖)的五个部分
In order for RNA to form,
five specific sugar molecules
需要自发的形成，
would have to
spontaneously come together,
一个接一个的以特定顺序形成。
one by one,
in a very particular order.
科学家认为在地球上的原始沼泽中
Scientist think
the odds of that happening
形成五碳糖是基本不可能的。
in earth's primordial swamp
were highly improbable.
你要等很久很久。
You would be waiting
for a very long time.
但是John认为应该会有
But John thought there may be
比核糖还简单的糖可以构成遗传物质，
a genetic material made
of a simpler sugar than ribose,
一些更有可能自发形成的。
something more likely to form
on its own.
通过在试管中重建进化过程，
By recreating evolution
in a test tube,
他可能发现了最合适的糖...
he may have found
the perfect fit...
形成TNA的糖。
a sugar that forms TNA.
[吹口哨]
[ Wolf whistle ]
不，不是那样的。
No, not that.
[女人笑声]
[ Woman giggles ]
TNA 即苏糖核酸。
TNA or Threose Nucleic Acid.
苏阿糖是很让人兴奋的，
Threose is very exciting,
因为化学成分上它比核糖简单。
because it's, chemically,
much simpler than ribose.
Freeman: John认为TNA更像是
Freeman: John thinks
TNA is a likely candidate
构成原始生命的候选人，
for being
the first spark of life
因为它是个四碳糖，
because it is made of
four identical sugar molecules
很容易就可以形成。
that come together
in just one easy step.
Chaput: 当你用苏糖核酸
Chaput: And when you make
a genetic polymer
构建成遗传分子，
out of threose nucleic acid,
它能与RNA的碱基良好匹配，
it turns out that it base pairs
very well with RNA,
所以TNA
so it has the ability
不仅比RNA有着更简单的化学结构，
to not only be
chemically simpler than RNA,
它还能够与RNA进行遗传信息交换。
but it can also exchange
genetic information with RNA.
Freeman: John可能发现了DNA的祖先，
Freeman: John may have found
an ancestor of DNA,
它是古老的生命蓝图，
an ancient genetic blueprint
that showed up
远早于我们现今的
long before
the complex machinery
复杂细胞结构。
that is in our cells today.
他还尚未证明TNA能够自我复制，
He has not yet been able to show
that TNA can copy itself,
但他认为TNA是迄今为止
but he believes
it is the best candidate so far
复杂生命前体的最好候选人。
to be the precursor
to complex life.
Chaput: 所以生命是如此复杂
Chaput: So, life in so complex
使得许多人认为肯定存在一个高层次力量，
that many people feel that
it must have had a higher power,
用神力创造了现有的生命。
a God-like power that helped
to create life as we know it.
但现实是，当你从比如化学的角度
But the reality is,
when you take a look at it
来看生命的诞生，
from the perspective of,
say, chemistry,
这的确是一个问题，
it's really a question
of what molecules
都存在过哪些分子，
might have been present
这些分子如何互相作用？
and how were these molecules
able to react with one another?
科学家瞄准了一种分子，
Scientists are zeroing in
on a molecule
它可能是地球上第一种遗传物质。
that may have been the first
genetic material on earth.
这会是生命的起源吗？
Would this be the spark of life?
也许需要比化学更深刻的答案。
Perhaps the answer
is deeper than chemistry.
如果生命起源
What if the origin of life
需要追溯到一个简单的规律呢，
can be traced back
to one simple pattern,
一个统治
a pattern that governs
整个宇宙结构的规律？
the structure
of the entire universe?
你看的每个地方
Imagine if everywhere you looked,
都能发现同样的规律...
you saw the same pattern...
天空中，地面上，
in the sky, on the ground,
你身体内。
in your body.
你可能认为这是一个伟大工匠的杰作。
You might wonder if it was
a signature of a craftsman.
实际上，宇宙中处处存在着这样的规律。
In fact, our universe really is
filled with such a pattern.
这就意味着某个伟大的设计者创造了一切吗?
Does this mean it must be
the work of a grand designer?
在Adrian Bejan成为杜克大学的工程学教授前，
Before Adrian Bejan became
a Professor of engineering
他从事着完全不同的职业。
at Duke university,
he had a very different career.
Adrian是罗马尼亚的明星篮球运动员。
Adrian was a basketball star
in Romania.
我是共产主义体制下的运动员，
I was a player
under the communist system.
但篮球运动不是共产主义。
Basketball is not communism.
尽管在共产主义制度下，
篮球运动也要正确的进行。
Even under communism,
basketball was played correctly.
在我篮球生涯中最重要的一课
The greatest single lesson
from growing up in basketball
就是篮球像水一样沿着渠道运动，
was the idea that the ball flows
through channels.
这些渠道并不是严格规定的，
The channels are not rigid.
它们在持续变化。
They are constantly morphing.
Freeman: 就像运动员Adrian把篮球
Freeman: Just as Adrian
the athlete saw basketball
看做是球场上的水流一样，
as the flow of a ball
across a court,
工程师Adrian现在研究着这样的流动。
Adrian the engineer
now studies that flow.
他认为这会是
He thinks it may be the key
了解整个宇宙设计的关键。
to understanding
the design of the universe.
篮球是一个活动的流动系统，
Basketball is
a live flow system.
它会从球场上任意一点流向球篮。
The ball flows from any point
of the area to the basket.
进攻队员试图打开这些渠道
The players on offense are
trying to open up the channels
来促使这种流动。
to facilitate the flow.
而同时防守队员
The players on defense,
at the same time,
试着关闭这些渠道。
are closing down the channels.
Freeman: 结果是越好的运动员就越频繁的得到篮球，
Freeman: Over time, the better
players get the ball more often,
使一些特定的渠道更宽阔繁忙，
making certain channels bigger
and busier
较不活跃的渠道保持其状态。
while the less active channels
stay smaller.
最终，就产生了规律，
Eventually, a pattern emerges
形成了分枝树结构。
that resembles the shape
of a branching tree.
这种树形结构无处不在。
This tree shape is everywhere.
它们数十亿次的反复出现。
They occur
in the billions and billions.
它们构成了自然界的一种现象。
They constitute
a phenomenon of all nature.
Freeman: Adrian看到了自然界中无处不在的规律，
Freeman: Adrian sees the same
pattern everywhere in nature,
从一棵树，到闪电，及叶脉。
from a tree to a lightning bolt
to the veins of a leaf.
他试着找出这种结构出自哪里。
He's trying to figure out
where this pattern comes from.
他认为这与物质
He thinks it has to do
从一点流向另一点的方式有关。
with the way things flow
from one point to another.
什么以树形结构流动呢？
What flows through the tree?
水从地面“流”向干燥的风中。
Water is flowing from the ground
back into the dry wind.
其他以树形结构流动的是
The other thing that flows
through the tree structure
机械力或机械应力。
is the mechanical force
or mechanical stresses.
风的力量通过树木
The force of the wind
is transmitted to the ground
传向地面。
through the tree.
Freeman: Adrian认为这种结构
Freeman: Adrian believes this design
是普遍自然法则的一种表现。
is an expression
of a universal law of nature.
他称之为结构法则。
He calls it the constructal law.
这表明通常情况下，
It states, most generally,
任何大小有限行为有限的东西，
that anything
that is finite size and moves,
为了与时间协调同步，
这也意味着生存，
in order to persist in time,
which means to live,
就必须进化出更加容易的
it must evolve such that
it flows more and more easily
随时间发展的更宽广的“渠道”。
for greater and greater access
over time.
Freeman: Adrian看到了我们身体内部
Freeman: Adrian sees evidence
of the constructal law
存在的结构法则。
inside of all of us.
氧气在肺中流动，血液在血管中流动，
Oxygen flows through our lungs,
blood flows through our veins,
电流沿神经元流动，
electricity flows
through our neurons,
全部以树形结构进行。
all in the same
tree-like design.
宇宙似乎就是这样创造出了复杂性，
The universe seems to be
hardwired to create complexity,
或者说宇宙是以这种方式被设计的。
almost as though
it was designed that way.
对于神创论的信仰者来说，
To a believer in creationism,
树形结构似乎是创造者的标志。
it would seem like
the mark of a creator.
Adrian并不这么认为。
Adrian says no.
Bejan: 这种设计就像地心引力现象一样，
Bejan: The design is a phenomenon
just like the gravitation fall.
我们并不知道这些性质为什么存在，
We do not know
why these things happen.
我们能做的就是总结这些现象，
All we can do is
to summarize these phenomena,
得出规律法则。
and those are the laws.
Freeman: Adrian认为树形结构
Freeman: Adrian thinks
this tree-shaped pattern
自然而然的创造了更强
更具适应性的生物体，
naturally creates stronger,
fitter organisms
因为它帮助了"流动"，
because it helps improve flow,
无论是水在树干中流动
whether it be water flowing
through the trunk of a tree
还是篮球在球场上向篮筐流动。
or the ball flowing
through the court to the hoop.
Bejan: 篮球实际上是一种
Bejan: Basketball
is actually a metaphor
社会中个体运动的比喻。
for the movement
of the individual in society.
这就像是个人顺着“渠道”流动，
It is the same kind of movement
through channels
并努力保持“渠道”的打开，
that the individual strives
to open up
同样的，其他人会在不经意间
and, at the same,
channels that others are,
关闭这些“渠道”。
in fact, unwittingly,
trying to close down.
Freeman: 也许宇宙的设计
Freeman: Perhaps
the design of the universe
像是一棵巨大的树...
is like a giant tree...
不断的通过增加流动生长、进化。
constantly growing and evolving
through improved flow.
但在南非，
But across the world
in South Africa,
一位宇宙学家正在通过不同的角度（镜头）
a cosmologist is looking
at the design of the universe
观察宇宙。
through a different lens.
[相机快门声]
[ Camera shutter clicking ]
他正在将自然法则倒置。
He's turning the laws of nature
upside down.
那些巨大而又复杂的东西是如何出现的呢？
How do large and complex things
come to be?
他们是许多微小事物的集合。
They're collections
of many little things.
身体由细胞构成，细胞由原子构成，
Bodies are made from cells,
and cells are built from atoms.
但组成我身体的原子并不知道它们是我的一部分，
But the atoms in my body
don't know they're part of me.
那它们如何知道自己要干嘛呢？
How do they know what to do?
为什么我不会崩坏成数以万亿的碎片？
Why don't I just fall apart
into a trillion tiny pieces?
它们是受到高层次力量的指引吗？
Are they being guided
by a higher power?
[合唱]
[ Choral singing ]
南非开普敦大学的George Ellis
George Ellis from the university
of cape town in South Africa
是物理学和宇宙学上
is one of
the world's leading theorists
世界前沿的理论学家。
in physics and cosmology.
最近，他把自己的关注点
Recently,
he has shifted his attention
从理解宇宙转向了
from trying to understand
the cosmos
理解地球上
to trying to understand
复杂系统是如何形成的，
how complex systems on earth
come to be,
比如开普敦青年合唱团的声音。
like the sounds
of the cape town youth choir.
[歌声持续]
[ Singing continues ]
对于George来说，动听的歌声可以
To George, a beautiful song
can be scientifically understood
以科学的方式理解。
in different ways.
曾作为物理学家的他
His old physicist self
能看到合唱中
would have seen the singing
of the choruses
体现出的亚原子水平的活动。
as emerging out of activity
at the subatomic level.
我认为物理学家会告诉你这里发生的
I think the physicist would tell
you what is happening here
是一些像电子或质子这样的
is the effect
of fundamental particles
基本粒子的相互作用。
interacting with each other
as electrons and protons.
这些年青人可以这么歌唱
That these youth
can sing this way
是由于他们的神经细胞传递电子，
is because in their nerve cells,
electrons are flowing
将电信号从脑传到其他神经中，
and they're sending signals down
from the brain to the nerves,
这些的基础其实都是物理学，
and so, it's physics
at the bottom, all the way,
是物理学使这一切正在发生。
and the physics is actually
what's causing it to happen.
Freeman: 但是George现在正思考
Freeman: But George now wonders
是否有其他的方式来理解合唱。
if there's another way
to understand the choir's music.
也许这些歌唱者并不仅仅是
Perhaps these singers aren't
一些亚原子物理过程的集合体。
just an aggregation
of subatomic physical processes.
因果流动
The flow of causation is
起始于指挥者，再到合唱的所有成员，
from the conductor
to all the members of the choir,
他是合唱者行为的协调者，
so he is coordinating
the chorister's actions,
人们大脑中的电子流动也是如此...
and so the flow of the electrons
in the people's brains...
它们可以由指挥者控制，
they're just responding
and being controlled
对指挥者想要的结果起反应。
by what the conductor
wanted to happen.
那么从顶部指挥者的想法开始，
So, it's top down
from the conductor's mind
向下传递到歌唱者脑中形成电子流。
into those electrons that are
flowing in people's brains.
Freeman: George称之为自上而下的因果关系。
Freeman: George calls this idea
top-to-bottom causation.
组成每位合唱者的基本粒子
The fundamental particles
that comprise each chorister
位于整个关系的最底层，
are the bottom level
由高层控制...
and are being controlled
by a higher level...
即指挥。
the conductor.
如果没有指挥，
If there were no conductor,
George 就需要堵住耳朵了。
George would need
some ear plugs.
[不和谐的歌声]
[ Discordant singing ]
Ellis: 你能得到的纯粹协同的
Ellis: The amount
of beauty coordination
上下关系的数量非常有限，
you can get purely bottom-up
is strictly limited.
你只能得到简单的协同，
You have to have
the simple coordination,
正是这种理念控制着物理学，
and it's the thought
that's controlling the physics
使物理事件得以发生。
and making the physics happen.
[相机快门声]
[ Camera shutter clicking ]
Freeman: 也许宇宙需要一个指挥，
Freeman: Perhaps the universe
needs a conductor
来创造我们身边美丽的大自然。
to create the beauty of nature
all around us.
George认为
And George thinks
在几何学中有证据
there is evidence
that this is true
证明这是真的。
in the form of geometry.
Ellis: 这是毕达哥拉斯定理，
Ellis: This is Pythagoras' theorem.
如果你已知一直角边长度，平方，
If you take that length,
square it,
再加上另一直角边的平方，
add it to that one squared,
就能得到直角三角形斜边的平方。
you get the square
on the hypotenuse.
这就是全宇宙
So that's an eternal principle
处处存在的永恒的定理。
which is true everywhere
in the universe.
Freeman: George认为宇宙存在一个几何学基础，
Freeman: George believes the
universe has an underlying geometry
统治着物理世界中发生的一切。
that governs what is possible
in the physical world.
他认为几何学法则早于我们宇宙而存在。
He thinks geometric laws existed
before our universe existed.
人类只是发现了这些法则而已。
Humans are only discovering them.
这起源于古希腊哲学家柏拉图的观点，
It's an idea that stems from
the Greek philosopher Plato,
柏拉图认为数学规则
who believed
mathematical patterns
早在宇宙诞生之前
existed in some abstract space
就已经存在。
before the birth
of our universe.
Ellis: 我也认为宇宙诞生之前，
Ellis: I think when the universe
was set up,
数学规则就已经存在。
the mathematical patterns
pre-existed the universe.
但不仅是这种物理学的东西存在，
But it isn't
only physical things that exist.
还有其他意义也已经存在。
There are also meanings
that exist.
Freeman: 就像柏拉图认为的，
Freeman: Just as Plato believed
宇宙伴随着数学真理而诞生，
the universe was born
with mathematical truths,
他认为人类伦理也是如此。
he said the same could be true
for human ethics.
对于George来说，这种哲学观点表明
To George, it is a philosophy
that suggests
我们的是非观源于一些永恒的真理，
our rules of right and wrong
may stem from some eternal truth
规定人们应该如何相处。
that dictates how humans
should treat each other.
Ellis: 这些道德规则早已设立，
Ellis: These ethical patterns
were set out there,
我认为其形成早于人类诞生之前。
in my opinion, before any human
beings ever existed.
经过了长期为了理解
I've arrived at this position
复杂性的努力研究，我现在是这么认为的，
through a long process of trying
to understand complexity,
因为很明显这种意义早已存在。
because it's quite clear
that there is meaning.
除了纯粹的力学原理还有很多的东西都已经存在。
There is more going on than this
purely mechanical kind of stuff.
Freeman: 有谁或什么东西创造了
Freeman: Did someone or something create
统治自然和社会的规则吗？
the laws that govern nature
and society?
人类伦理是一种生命由其他高等道德生命
Are human ethics a sign
that life was designed
创造的标志吗？
by a moral being?
还是道德只是进化的产物？
Or is morality
a product of evolution?
加利福尼亚的这个人
One man in California
正在迈出回答这个问题的巨大一步。
is taking a giant leap of faith
to find out.
进化论寻找的是对所有生命形式的解释。
Evolutionary theory seeks to
explain life in all its forms.
而神学寻找的不仅仅是
But in theology,
there's more to creation
我们肉体形成的解释。
than our physical bodies.
神是宇宙道德的主宰者。
God is master
of our moral universe.
道德是在人脑中
Can morality arise
in the human brain
由一些生物进化中偶然出现的进程建立的吗？
by the haphazard process
of biological evolution
或是早已被设计好的？
or was it designed?
[禽鸟鸣叫]
[ Bird screeches ]
Paul Zak教授是克莱蒙研究大学的
Professor Paul Zak from
claremont graduate university
一名前沿科学家。
is a scientist on the frontier.
他是神经经济学领域的先驱，
He's a pioneer of a field
called neuroeconomics,
这门学科主要研究脑内的化学成分
which is the study
of how brain chemistry
是如何影响人们的日常决策的。
affects people's decisions
in life.
他最近研究的问题正是人类道德的起源。
His latest quest is for
the origin of human morality.
我的母亲在生我之前是一名天主教修女，
My mother, before she was my
mother, was a nun, a catholic nun.
那我母亲就是道德世界的标准。
So, mom was the ruler
of the morality world.
而我内心有一些想法，
I really had
this underlying kind of worry
难道没有很多形式的道德标准吗？
that aren't there many different
forms of morality?
正与邪从何而来？
Where do good and evil
come from?
这也是我花费时间精力
And that's the question
进行实验想要验证的问题。
I really spent my time running
experiments to identify.
Freeman: 	Paul认为可能
Freeman: Paul thinks there might be
有一种分子产生了道德。
a single molecule
responsible for morality.
他在研究中发现了一种分子...
His research has led him
to one possible candidate...
一个脑内叫做“催产素”的化学成分。
a brain chemical
called oxytocin.
Zak: 催产素是脑垂体产生的化学分子，
Zak: Oxytocin is a chemical
the brain makes
直至十年前，这种分子的作用还只认为
that, until about 10 years ago,
was only noted in humans
是促进生产和乳汁分泌。
to facilitate birth
and breast feeding.
当我开始着手这项工作时，
So, when I first started doing
this work,
我的一个同事说，
one of my colleagues said,
“如果只有女性可以分泌这种激素，
那么它就不会很重要。”
"it can't be that important
if it's only for women, "
不过事实上男性也会分泌。
but, in fact,
men's brains make it, too.
问题就是为什么。
催产素到底发挥了什么功能呢？
The question was why.
Is it actually doing something?
Freeman: Paul认为如果催产素的功能
Freeman: Paul wondered
if oxytocin had a larger role
不仅仅是帮助生产，
than aiding in reproduction,
那么它就可能让人们感到
that perhaps it helps
all humanity
同情、爱与信任。
feel compassion, love,
and trust.
为了找出答案，他进行了一项长期试验，
In order to find out,
he began a long-term study
检测当一个人被迫去相信陌生人时
of how this brain chemical
fluctuates
这种脑化学成分是如何波动的。
when a person is forced to trust
a stranger.
今天，他的实验对象就是自己。
Today, his test subject is himself.
我们今天打算去跳伞，
We're gonna go skydiving today
to find out
来看当人们面对其他人时的
what happens to the human brain
when you're under high stress
高度紧张环境中的脑部反应。
in the presence
of another person.
我们已经在实验室中证明了
So, we've shown in a laboratory
催产素可以促使对陌生人的信任，
that oxytocin facilitates trust
in strangers,
那么把你的生命托付于陌生人又会如何呢？
so how about trusting your life
to a stranger?
这就是我们今天想要测试的。
That's what we want to test today.
Freeman: Paul首先在地面上
Freeman: Paul first takes a sample
采集了自己的血液样本。
of his own blood on the ground.
这个样本会作为催产素的基本水平，
This will be used as
the baseline level of oxytocin
这样就能在他着陆返回后进行对比。
so he can compare it to
his blood levels when he lands.
串联跳伞是信任的终极测试。
Tandem skydiving is
the ultimate test of trust.
两个人，一个降落伞。
Two people, one parachute.
Paul的生命就在他的指导员Andy的手中。
Paul's life is in the hands
of his instructor, Andy.
这位就是Andy，这也是我第一次见他，
So, this is Andy. So, I've just
met him for the first time,
我会把自己和他绑在一起，
and I'm gonna strap myself
to him
在12,500英尺的高空中跳出飞机，
and jump out of an airplane
at 12,500 feet,
我不知道你是如何训练的，
so I don't know
how you're trained.
我不认识飞行员，我不知道谁包装的你的降落伞。
I don't know the pilot. I don't
know who packed your chute.
这个我也不知道。
I don't even know that, either.
[笑]是的，好的，那么...
[ Chuckling ] Yeah, okay, so...
经过在地面的简单辅导，
After a brief coaching session
on the ground,
他们就要飞上天了。
there's nowhere left to go
but up.
大多数跳伞事故都是人为错误...
Most skydive accidents
happen from human error...
比如降落伞的包装不妥，
improper packing
of the parachute,
检查不足，缺乏跳伞技巧等。
inadequate inspection,
poor jumping technique.
Paul将他的信任交给一组陌生人。
Paul is putting his trust
into a crew of strangers.
我不认为我还有别的选择。
I don't think I have a choice.
现在我必须相信Andy，
I really got to trust Andy now,
我只是希望一切都能顺利。
so I'm just hoping
it all works out.
准备好了吗？
Ready to do this?
开始吧！
Let's go!
好的！
All right!
让我们开始吧。
Let's do it, baby.
哦，看这场面。
Oh, look at that view.
已经准备好了。
Hands on the harness.
做个深呼吸。
Take a nice, deep breath.
好的。
Yeah.
现在我们找些乐子吧。
Now for some fun.
好的，哥们儿。
All right, man.
头往右。
Head to the right.
[叫喊声]
[ Yells ]
哇！
Whoa!
做得好，你可以解开了。
Well done. You're unhooked.
好的。
All right.
欢迎继续你的余生。
Welcome
to the rest of your life.
谢谢。
Thank you. Okay.
Freeman: 落地之后，Paul马上采集了血液样本。
Freeman: After the jump, Paul
immediately draws his blood again.
Zak: 我和那个人绑在一起，在12,000尺的高度，
Zak: I was strapped to this guy,
12,000 feet.
我们像石头一样离开了飞机...
You know, we dropped like a rock
out of this airplane...
很不寻常的感受，
very unusual kind of event
眼看着飞机离我而去...
where I'm watching the plane
move away from me...
有些慌乱与恐惧。
kind of panic, kind of fear.
Freeman: Paul将自己的血液样本带回了实验室，
Freeman: Paul brings his
blood samples back to his lab
来看紧张情感下的信任
to find out if
the intense feeling of trust
能否在脑化学中体现出来。
was reflected
in the chemistry of his brain.
正如预料一样，跳出飞机后
As one might expect after
jumping out of an airplane,
Paul的肾上腺皮质醇(一种压力激素)增加了5倍，
Paul had almost a 500% increase
in cortisol, a stress hormone,
睾丸酮增加了40%，
and a 40% increase
in testosterone,
这又与胆量与勇气相关。
which is associated
with the feeling of courage.
但跳伞是否引起了道德分子
But did the skydive
cause a moral molecule
开始发挥作用呢？
to jump into action?
Zak: 我的催产素增加了17%，
Zak: I had about a 17% increase
in oxytocin.
17%对于与陌生人的交流来说
17% is actually
a fairly large increase
的确算是很明显的增加。
for an interaction
with a stranger.
举个例子，我去过的一个新娘的结婚典礼上...
So, for example, at a bride
at her wedding that I went to...
我采集了之前和之后的血样...
I took blood before and after...
我发现她(因为爱)的催产素增加了28%。
I found that she had a 28% increase.
我与我的跳伞指导员的联系
So, I'm half as connected
to my skydive instructor
是新娘与婚礼上新郎联系的一半，
as the bride was to her groom
at her wedding,
结果还算不错。
so that ain't bad.
Freeman: Paul的研究表明
Freeman: Paul's studies have shown
催产素水平与其他社会行为人
that oxytocin levels
are strongly linked
有着强烈的关联，不仅是信任，
to other social behaviors
besides trust,
还有同理心(移情作用)和慷慨。
like empathy and generosity.
如果催产素是控制我们道德行为的分子，
If oxytocin is the molecule that
controls our moral behavior,
那么这种分子又从何而来？
where did this molecule
come from?
它会是渴望道德社会的造物主设计的吗？
Was it designed by a creator
who yearned for a moral society?
Zak: 我想谦卑的说，“我并不知道
Zak: I want to be humble
and say, "Look, I don't know
“在进化之前都发生了什么，
"What happened before evolution
started happening,
“如果真有上帝，这一切又会多么美妙。”
and if there's a God,
how wonderful is that?"
但作为科学家我无法评论
but it's not my place
as a scientist
神是否存在。
to say whether God exists
or not.
我认为这是信仰的问题。
I think that's a question of faith.
Freeman: 我们脑中的道德分子
Freeman: Is a moral molecule
in our brains
是神创造了我们的标志吗？
the sign that we are designed
by a holy God?
还是我们的脑就这么进化...
Or did our brains evolve
that way...
使得我们能够团结生存？
allowing us to survive
together as a species?
如果是催产素让我们信任和容忍别人，
If it is oxytocin that makes us
trust and tolerate one another,
也许这种分子就能够
maybe this single molecule
is the answer
将神创论者和进化论者整合在一起。
to bringing creationists
and evolutionists together.
神创论者认为只有神的指引
Creationists argue that
only the guiding hand of God
才能将宇宙中无尽的原子整理成
could arrange the countless
atoms of the cosmos
今日我们看到的非凡景象，
into the remarkable pattern
that exists today,
道德分子只可能在道德宇宙中形成。
that moral molecules would
only form in a moral universe.
进化论则指出了一个简单的规则...
The theory of evolution argues
that one simple rule...
适者生存...
survival of the fittest...
这样就能解释现有的一切吗，
can explain everything
that lives today,
从最贪婪的捕食者
from the most rapacious predators
到我们这样由内心深处
何为正邪的感受
to beings like us
who are guided by a deep sense
所指引的人类。
of what is right
and what is wrong.
这场争论不会很快就结束，
The debate isn't likely
to end any time soon,
但有一点是双方都赞同的...
but there is one thing
both sides do agree on...
即生命存在的伟大奇迹，
无论它是如何出现的。
the sheer wonder of creation,
no matter how it got here.